Guide to the Cadell & Davies Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Cadell & Davies records
1767-1831
GEN MSS 510
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.67
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, promissory notes, receipts, and statements of account documenting the publishing and bookselling business of Cadell & Davies. The records include letters from contemporary authors and printers, as well as substantial correspondence with the poet and novelist Charlotte Turner Smith. Other correspondents include Edward Daniel Clarke, George Huntingford, William Magee, Edward Maltby, Isaac Milner, Charles Simeon, and Nathaniel Wraxall.
Cadell & Davies
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Library Associates (purchased from Stonehill), 1939.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
CADELL & DAVIES
The British publishing and bookselling firm of Cadell & Davies was established in 1793 when Thomas Cadell the elder (1742-1802) retired from the publishing world, bequeathing his business to his apprentice, William Davies (d. 1820), and his son, Thomas Cadell (1773-1836). The new partners located their firm on the Strand in London, with Davies managing most of the partnership's affairs until he became ill in 1813. Cadell consequently became more involved with the firm's business, establishing himself and the publishing house as major players in the London book trade. After Davies's death in 1820, Cadell began publishing under his own name.
The firm was dissolved in 1836 when Thomas Cadell died, although several years passed before the Cadell imprint disappeared. Remaining stocks and copyrights were sold in 1840.
For additional information, see The Publishing Firm of Cadell & Davies: Select Correspondence and Accounts, 1793-1836, edited with an introduction and notes by Theodore Besterman (London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1938).
Scope and Contents
The Cadell & Davies Records consist primarily of correspondence, receipts, bank notes and legal agreements relating to the publishing and bookselling business of Cadell & Davies. The records are organized into one series, Series I. Business Files, and are alphabetically arranged by correspondent. The papers span the dates 1767 to 1831 though the bulk of the material falls in the period 1790 to 1820.
Incoming correspondence from authors and prospective book purchasers, some annotated by the publishers, is interfiled with copies of replies written by Thomas Cadell and William Davies. The records also include a few letters addressed to the elder Thomas Cadell, as well as notes from printers such as Richard Watts and Luke Hansard. These letters have been interfiled chronologically within the correspondence files.
The correspondence typically concerns negotiations between the author and Cadell & Davies. The letters offer insight into the complex network of relations among printer, engraver, publisher, and author; the roles that subscribers and patrons played in supporting the printing of specific works; the impact that advertising and literary reviews were believed to have on sales; and the difficulties of contemporary transport. The records also detail financial transactions, printing expenses, and the firm's contractual arrangements with authors and other booksellers.
The largest single correspondence is that between Charlotte Turner Smith and Cadell & Davies, which numbers over 130 letters, and provides an ongoing account of the circumstances prompting her literary career. In a letter dated October 20, 1797, she wrote that she was "too acutely sensible of the misery, the humiliation of being compelled, with so handsome a fortune of my own, and such claims on behalf of my children to be dependent on my writing... doomed from year to year to invent fable for the public & to take as a favor any price offered." The correspondence also includes Charlotte Smith's opinions of her worth as a writer, details about her family life and writing process, and information about the publication of Elegiac Sonnets (1789-1800), Rural Walks (1795), and Rambles Farther (1800).
The records also contain a significant amount of correspondence between Cadell & Davies and the travel writer Edward Daniel Clarke, primarily regarding the publication of his Travels (1810-1824) and ongoing contractual disputes. The historian Nathaniel Wraxhall's letters offer heated commentary on the Napoleonic Wars (1800-1815). Other correspondents with substantial material include George Huntingford, William Magee, Edward Maltby, Isaac Milner, and Charles Simeon.
Wrappers that previously enclosed the records have been placed at the end of the series in two folders. These wrappers include earlier cataloging information and occasionally provide biographical notes about correspondents.
Authors and publishers -- England -- London; Authors, English -- 19th century; Booksellers and bookselling -- England -- London; Publishers and publishing -- England -- London; Promissory notes; Receipts (financial records); Adolphus, John, 1768-1845; Barrow, John, Sir, 1764-1848; Bowdler, H. M. (Henrietta Maria), 1750-1830; Cadell, T. (Thomas), 1742-1802; Cadell, Thomas, 1773-1836; Clarke, Edward Daniel, 1769-1822; Coxe, William, 1747-1828; Davies, William, -1820; Gisborne, Thomas, 1758-1846; Huntingford, George Isaac, 1748-1832; Magee, William, 1766-1831; Maltby, Edward, 1770-1859; Milner, Isaac, 1750-1820; Mitford, William, 1744-1827; Pinkerton, John, 1758-1826; Pretyman, George, 1750-1827; Redesdale, John Mitford, Baron, 1748-1830; Simeon, Charles, 1759-1836; Smith, Charlotte, 1749-1806; Wraxall, Nathaniel William, Sir, 1751-1831; Cadell & Davies
- Business Files, 1767-1831; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Business Files, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - ADOLPHUS, JOHN, 1768-1845
    - Correspondence, 1797-1812 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Contains 3 ALS to Cadell and Davies and copies of 2 ALS to John Adolphus.
    - Receipts and notes, 1797-1806 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      23 receipts, notes, etc. drawn between John Adolphus and Cadell and Davies.
    - Autograph note concerning publication of the works of John Adolphus, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AIKEN, JOHN, 1747-1822
    - Autograph receipt, signed, issued to Cadell and Davies, London, April 20, 1801, and two promissory notes payable to him, with his endorsement, 1801, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - BARRETT, JOHN, 1753-1821
    - ALS to Cadell and Davies, [Dublin], 1805 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - BARROW, JOHN, SIR, 1764-1848
    - 12 ALS to Cadell and Davies, London, 1803-06 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Autograph copy, signed, of the title page of Travels in China, with chapter headings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Financial accounts of Africa and China (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - BOWDLER, H. M. (HENRIETTA MARIA), 1754-1830
    - Correspondence, 1801-10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Contains 9 ALS to Cadell and Davies, Bath; ALS from Stuart Cheyne to Cadell and Davies regarding publication of Bowdler's Sermons, dated 1803 Apr 19; ALS from [J?] Smith to Cadell and Davies, dated 1807 Nov 27.
  - CLARKE, EDWARD DANIEL, 1769-1822
    - Correspondence, 1805-07 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes ALS from J. Clarke to Mr. Davies, Petworth, dated Sep 5 and ALS from R. Watts, printer, to Cadell and Davies, Cambridge, dated Aug 10.
    - Correspondence, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1812-13 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1819-21, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 6 statements of accounts, promissory notes, receipts, etc., 1805-12 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - COXE, WILLIAM, 1747-1828
    - Correspondence, 1804-11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 15 promissory notes and receipts drawn between William Coxe and Cadell and Davies, 1796-1811 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - DALLAS, ROBERT CHARLES, 1754-1824
    - ALS to Cadell and Davies, [London], 1801 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - DRAKE, NATHAN, 1766-1836
    - Correspondence, 1800-09 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Includes 3 ALS from J. Burkitt to Cadell and Davies regarding the printing of Nathan Drake's works, Suffolk.
    - 4 promissory notes drawn between Nathan Drake and Cadell and Davies, 1804 Jan 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Statement of account between Nathan Drake and Cadell and Davies (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - GIFFORD, JOHN, 1758-1818
    - Memorandum of an agreement drawn between John Gifford and Henry Redhead York on the one part and the Messrs. Thomas Cadell and William Davies on the other part, London (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Regarding the publication of Life of William Pitt., n.d.
  - GILPIN, WILLIAM, 1724-1804
    - 7 promissory notes and drafts drawn between William Gilpin and Cadell and Davies, London, 1796-1801 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - GISBORNE, THOMAS, 1758-1846
    - Correspondence, 1796-1823 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
      Includes anonymous AL to Thomas Gisborne, Birmingham, dated 1797 Dec 18.
  - HARRIS, JAMES, 1709-1780
    - ALS to an unidentified correspondent, "Sarum 15 1767" (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - HUNTINGFORD, GEORGE ISAAC, 1748-1832
    - Correspondence, 1796-1811 (Box 2, Folder 33-36)
      Includes: ALS to Cadell and Davies from Henry Huntingford regarding publication of works by his uncle, George Huntingford, Winchester, dated 1806 Feb 18; 2 ALS regarding proof sheets of Bishop Huntingford's work. One is signed "Saml. Collingwood" and the other "L[uke] H[ansard]"; ALS from J. Burdon to Cadell and Davies regarding the printing of George Huntingford's works, Winchester, dated 1800 Jan 22.
    - Autograph list of works of George Huntingford published by Cadell and Davies (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - MACLAINE, ARCHIBALD, 1722-1804
    - 2 ALS to Cadell and Davies, Bath, 1798, 1800 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      First letter cut in two, part missing.
  - MAGEE, WILLIAM, 1766-1831
    - Correspondence, 1804-06 (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
    - Correspondence, 1810 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence, 1811-14 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence, 1815-19 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Printing proof sheets, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - MALTBY, EDWARD, 1770-1859
    - Correspondence, 1804 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence, 1806 (Box 2, Folder 47-48)
    - Correspondence, 1809-11 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence, 1815-20 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence, 1821 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence, 1824-25 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence, 1828-29 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Includes ALS to R. Watts from Cadell and Davies, dated 1829 Feb 23.
      3 ALS from R. Watts, printer, enclosed with letter from Cadell and Davies, dated 1829 Apr 2.
    - List of correspondence, 1824 Aug (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - MILNER, ISAAC, 1750-1820
    - Correspondence, 1804-09 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence, 1810 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Correspondence, 1813, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Memorandum for an agreement between Dean Milner and Cadell and Davies, London, 1808 Jun 8 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - MITFORD, WILLIAM, 1744-1827
    - Correspondence, 1803-08 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Correspondence, 1809-26 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Notes on writings, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - ORME, ROBERT, 1728-1801
    - Correspondence, 1782-94 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - OUSELEY, WILLIAM, SIR, 1767-1842
    - 2 ALS to Cadell and Davies, London (Box 3, Folder 63)
      Includes newspaper clipping advertising one of his works.
    - 4 receipts to Cadell and Davies, London, 1799-1800 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - OWEN, JOHN, 1766-1822
    - Promissory note to Mrs. Mary Wilson, Fulham, 1796 Jul 11 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - PINKERTON, JOHN, 1758-1826
    - Correspondence, 1804-06 (Box 3, Folder 66)
      Includes ALS from John Pinkerton to John Spottiswoode, Paris, dated 1805 Jan.
    - Correspondence, 1808-10, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Arbitration bond between Pinkerton and Cadell and Davies, London, 1804 Mar 17 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Promissory note, payable to John Pinkerton, signed by Cadell and Davies, 1802 May 1 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Printing proof sheets, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - PRETYMAN, GEORGE, 1750-1827
    - Correspondence, 1799-1821 (Box 3, Folder 71-72)
    - Statements for cost of printing, 1803, 1809, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - PROUT, SAMUEL, 1783-1852
    - ALS to Arthur Glennie, Brixton, [1828 May] (Box 3, Folder 74)
      Regarding Glennie's education.
  - RAFFLES, THOMAS, 1788-1863
    - ALS to James Moyes, Liverpool, 1834 Jan 20 (Box 3, Folder 75)
      Regarding Raffles's collection of autographs.
  - RAPHOE, W. [?]
    - ALS apparently to Cadell and Davies, 1821 Dec 26 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - REDESDALE, JOHN MITFORD, BARON, 1748-1830
    - Correspondence, 1817-28 (Box 3, Folder 77-79)
  - RUSSELL, WILLIAM, 1741-1793
    - 6 ALS to George Robinson, Knottyholm, 1788-93 (Box 3, Folder 80-81)
    - Printing proof sheets, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - SIMEON, CHARLES, 1759-1836
    - Correspondence, 1805-06 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Correspondence, 1808-09 (Box 3, Folder 84)
      Includes 2 ALS from L[uke] H[ansard] to W. Davies, dated 1808 Jan 26 and 1808 Feb 7.
    - Correspondence, 1815 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Correspondence, 1816-18 Mar (Box 3, Folder 86)
      Includes ALS written for Mrs. Brown, printer, to Cadell and Davies.
    - Correspondence, 1818 Apr-Dec (Box 3, Folder 87)
      Includes ALS from Luke Hansard to W. Davies, dated 1818 Dec 20.
    - Correspondence, 1819 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Correspondence, 1820-21 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Correspondence, 1823 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Correspondence, 1824-26 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Correspondence, 1827-28 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Correspondence, 1831 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 94)
      Includes ALS from Luke Hansard to Cadell and Davies; ALS from Charles Rivington regarding Simeon's work.
    - Two statements of account between Charles Simeon and Cadell and Davies, 1809 Jan 18, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - SINCLAIR, JOHN, SIR, 1754-1835
    - 4 ALS to Cadell and Davies, Edinburgh, 1800-02 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Two statements of account between Sir John Sinclair and Cadell and Davies, 1803 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - SMITH, C. M.
    - 2 ALS to Cadell and Davies, Heddington, [1797] Aug 23, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 98)
      Together with a note written in the third person to Cadell & Davies, Tilford, 1805 Aug 17, probably in the handwriting of C. M. Smith.
  - SMITH, CHARLOTTE TURNER, 1749-1806
    - Correspondence, 1791-94 (Box 3, Folder 99-101)
    - Correspondence, 1795 (Box 3, Folder 102-103)
    - Correspondence, 1796 (Box 4, Folder 104-105)
    - Correspondence, 1797 (Box 4, Folder 106-108)
    - Correspondence, 1799 (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Correspondence, 1800-06 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 111-113)
      Includes 2 notes written in the the third person, one possibly by Mr. Parkyn; ALS from Sir Lionel Smith, son of CS; and ALS from Lucy Smith, daughter of CS.
    - Receipts and statements of account (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Recipient lists for presentation copies, 1794, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - 27 promissory notes drawn between Charlotte Smith and Cadell and Davies, 1794-98 (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - SOTHEBY, WILLIAM, 1757-1833
    - ALS to Cadell and Davies (Box 4, Folder 117)
      Together with a copy of AL from Cadell and Davies to William Sotheby, dated 1802 Jul 19.
  - TOMLINE, GEORGE PRETYMAN, SIR, 1750-1827
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: George Pretyman, box 3, folders 71-73
  - VINCENT, WILLIAM, 1739-1815
    - Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - WOODHOUSELEE, ALEXANDER FRASER TYTLER, LORD
    - Correspondence, 1811-13 (Box 4, Folder 119)
      Enclosed are 4 ALS from William Fraser Tytler and William Creech, pertaining to the works of Lord Woodhouselee.
  - WRAXALL, NATHANIEL WILLIAM, SIR, 1751-1831
    - Correspondence, 1799-1800 (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Correspondence, 1801-06 (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - Correspondence, 1807-15 (Box 4, Folder 122-124)
    - Correspondence, 1816-17 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Correspondence, 1818-21, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - RELATED MATERIAL
    - Wrappers with cataloging information, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 127-128)